Hello, welcome everyone. This is active
guest stream 124.1.
It's December 4th, 2025. Interesting.
124.
Good. And Ty Roachford will be
presenting on a recent paper PCT verse
FP a comparison between reorganization
theory and basian inference. There will
be a presentation followed by some
remarks from our panelists and questions
and I will also look in the live chat
for any questions. So thank you Ty and
Warren and Andreas for joining and to
you Ty for the presentation.
>> Absolutely
happy to be here. So this is my
presentation on recent paper perceptual
control theory versus free energy
principle comparison between
regularization theory and basian
inference. I did wrote this paper with
my collaborator Warren Menzel and my PI
Dr. Rodrigo Penna. So getting into it
this is how the paper looks. We
published over in MDPI foundations
and [clears throat]
what we did was a full stack comparison
where we looked at the philosophy, the
modeling and the mathematics around both
perceptual control theory and the free
energy principle. [snorts]
And we're going to get into sort of what
these two pictures, what all these
pictures sort of mean in the context of
the presentation here.
So to start off with, I think that there
are a lot of scientific explanations
that I would call principlebased
frameworks where instead of looking at a
bunch of data and then creating theories
and models based off of that, it sort of
flips the whole entire thing on its head
and we're going from principles theories
models really theories and models
constrained by principles to data that
is being generated by those models. So
in other words, we use principles to
constrain the space of models that we're
actually considering when we go out to
model something that is in the world.
And in physics, this has already been a
thing. This has been a thing for sure in
both physics and biology. So here are
just some examples [clears throat] of
that. conservation of energy, the
maximum entropy principle, the principle
of least action and in biology having
things like autopoesis,
self-organization, homeostasis and also
natural selection.
So getting into perceptual control
theory as a principle-based framework,
we could say that the principle of
perceptual control theory is behavior is
the control of perception. So rather
than looking at organisms as if they're
say computers or particular functions
that take an input and give a specific
output given that input every single
time deterministically rather you should
look at organisms as dedicated to
controlling what their input is rather
than their output.
And so the idea is that more like a
thermostat that controls the
temperature, you can look at an organism
like this in that when the temperature
comes into the thermostat or even the
organism as we see on the bottom here.
What's happening is it's going to give a
response or a behavior that brings it
towards
that allows it to affect the temperature
such that it minimizes the difference
between its internal set point of 72 in
this case and the outside temperature
that it's sensing. So in other words, if
it's far too cold, if it's 60° that
comes in here and we have a 72°ree set
point, well, we're not responding
specifically to the fact that it is 60°.
We're responding to the fact that
there's a difference between our
internal set point of 72 and 60 and
there would be a different response if
our internal set point was now at 75
rather than 60. So the output is
actually depending on this discrepancy
between the sensed temperature and the
internal reference point that is
associated with that temperature. And
the same thing goes on in organisms but
a bit more complicated where we have
multiple variables, internal variables
that we're regulating such as hunger and
temperature and many other things for
many more complicated organisms. And
these are all in conflict. So the
organism doesn't simply
try to do them all at the same time. It
sort of prioritizes certain ones over
the other in certain contexts, which is
what makes organisms so much more
difficult to understand. But being that
you identify [snorts] something as a
control system, it's much easier to then
understand it that way rather than as a
domino effect where it's just an input
leading straight up to an output.
And this leads me to this notion that
perceptual control theory has. It's
called the test for controlled variable
where you identify whether something is
indeed a control system or if it's just
a computer domino effect like thing. So
on the top of this panel here figure
here I have this input output system
causation paradigm where you can see a
cause or a sensory input coming into
some organism which we denote here as a
mechanism and it caused the observed
behavior. What you end up actually
seeing the organism do and typically
people label the sensory input as the
cause and the effect as the observed
behavior that you see. But when you're
looking at a control system this is not
really the case. It's more the case that
like I said because the cause is
actually the discrepancy between the
sense temperature and the internal
reference variable that's happening
inside the organism and the effect
that's produced happens inside the
organism as well. But there is external
side effects or consequences that you
can see as a result of what is going on
internally to keep this variable this
input in the way that the organism would
like it to be. So what you're actually
really seeing here relabeled in this
diagram is that your sensory input what
you thought was a sensory input or the
cause is more like a disturbance to the
reference variable that is being set in
the control system. And again the
observed behavior being side effects of
what it does to bring that reference
variable into alignment with the sensed
variable.
Okay. And this leads to something called
the behavioral illusion where just if
you mistake a control system for an open
loop then you're thinking that you've
isolated the cause of some effect in the
organism but you actually have not.
You've been misled.
So getting into the diagram here of how
perceptual control theory likes to look
at organisms and things, natural control
systems, control systems that have been
not made by a human but came up through
evolution. Well, they break it into
system and environment where we're
really focused on the measurable
quantities that are in the environment
and how they're being disturbed and how
that ends up changing the behavior of
the system that embedded in the
environment. So, what we have here is
the input quantity and this could be
something like temperature and then we
also have a disturbance to that
temperature. So opening a window would
disturb the thermostat's ability to
regulate temperature because it would
sense that there's temperature value has
deferred. We have an input function here
that takes the sensor variable outside
and converts it into a perceptual signal
that it then compares with the reference
signal P P star and produces an error
which goes into an output function that
affects then some other variable which
could be somehow the the temperature
directly but really it goes through some
sort of physical [clears throat] some
sort of physical chain of events that
might be causing it to open a window or
turn on a furnace, heat up some coils,
something like this, which eventually
goes down and affects that input
temperature, that input quantity that
it's using to create its actual
perception of what's going on.
And so this is the canonical perceptual
control theory diagram that we see in
the literature.
An interesting thing about perceptual
control theory too, just to hopefully
really separate the difference between
control system approaches and um
analytical or computer openloop
approaches is this idea versus of
analytical versus non-analytical
solutions. So the outfielder problem
really illustrates this well where it's
how do agents track and catch flying
objects? Someone hits a baseball, it
goes flying. What does an organism
actually do to then go and actually
track and catch that object? Well, one
way of thinking of it, the analytical or
openloop computer perspective, is it
something hits the ball and it measures
the angle, the initial speed, etc. So
forth takes those variables, plugs them
into Newton's equations. Like literally,
it has some sort of Newton's equation
form machine. I mean, maybe it's made
out of biological materials, but that's
what it does. It measures those initial
conditions, puts them in there, turns it
forward until the ball lands, and goes,
"Okay, I'm going to go to that
particular spot. I'm going to run there,
and that's how I'm going to catch the
ball." And like, maybe this could work,
but there's all these sorts of
influences from wind if you don't get
your initial conditions measurements
right, and things can just change over
time. So, it's not a very good solution.
And you could imagine, oh well, maybe
let's just measure it through time, over
time as the ball is flying. Well, like
yes, but again, it's kind of a little
bit maybe expensive a lot. Like now
you're computing the same problem over
and over and over again in case
something changes just in so it's not
very efficient. It's not a um solution
that is [sighs and gasps] I expect to be
in organisms because it's very expensive
and there could be a simpler cheaper way
and the simpler cheaper way is a sort of
non-analytical solution where instead of
having this explicit model you're doing
something more like coupling to the
system that you're engaging with in a
simplified way so that you can achieve
the same solution. So in this case a
non-analytical solution would be optical
acceleration cancellation where what
happens is the person hits the ball the
ball goes flying and you see the ball
and if it's going faster and faster
according to your point of view then you
know you need to speed up your running
right and if it's slowing down because
it'll land behind you and if it's
slowing down then it's going to land in
front of you. So that means you need to
slow down. So just by speeding up and
slowing down, you can make sure that
you're right there keeping a constant
velocity and eventually you'll catch the
ball when it reaches the the position
where you're at.
And this non analytical solution is more
what perceptual control theory thinks
that organisms employ and uses its tests
to be able to handle and develop models
of.
And now for the main thing of perceptual
control theory when it comes to learning
and actually getting to these sorts of
solutions that allow you to solve
problems with [clears throat] a low
amount of information or specific data
um not doing this analytical method.
Well, we have typically in organisms,
like I said, not just a thermostat, but
multiple competing different variables,
and they're all wrapped up into this
sort of hierarchy where you have higher
levels of control systems feeding
reference signals to the control systems
at lower levels and ultimately causing
the behavior of the thing to happen. And
we have this sort of complex
organization here where you have these
control systems.
And [clears throat] what happens is that
when the air starts to grow a lot and
it's beyond some threshold, whatever it
is that has been determined by
evolution, then there is an idea that
comes from sort of negentropy. This idea
of negative entropy, some way to push
ourselves um away from dissipating that
brings us to change the organization
between control units or perhaps even
some parameters of control units such
that the error ceases or at least goes
down in its rate of increase
significantly before we're stopping
again. And in fact, what people look at
is [clears throat]
say in the case of catching a fly ball,
reorganization theory would say perhaps
something like if you didn't know how to
catch a fly ball, then your brain would
reorganize in such a way that you
identified the sort of optical
acceleration canulation
solution to allow you to catch the ball.
And once you had done that, once you had
gotten there, then your behavior that is
being produced by this perception,
[clears throat]
your behavior that is being produced by
this perception
would be able to allow you to actually
catch the ball. So, let me rephrase this
is that the behavior that you're seeing
when a person is catching the ball is
due to ongoing sort of reorganization
where they're constantly um learning and
adjusting their parameters to allow this
error to cease to grow.
And the way that they're doing that, the
way they end up kind of settling on to
this particular information or solution,
I think is finding control
informationheavy knobs. And so control
information is this sort of attribute
between the relationship of things. It's
not about the sorts of many possible
states that a thing could actually be
in. Rather, [clears throat]
it's about how the organization of
things allow, say, small bits of
information to move a ton of mass in a
way that moves some cybernetic or
purposive system towards achieving its
goals. And this was made by Corning
where they have this paper called
control information theory the missing
link in the science of cybernetics
and in that they define control
information further as the quantity of
available energy that can be controlled
by a given unit of information in a
given context and typically it's talked
about as the relationship between a
control system and something in the
environment some particular information
in the environment and it's talking
about whether whether or not that
information can get an organism to
achieve the particular task.
Okay, so essentially control information
and reorganization theory I feel like
have a really good and interesting match
here and um
it's sort of answering the question what
or looking to answer the question or
describing what informationational bits
move the system towards its goal most
quickly. Well, it would be
theformational bits that allow you to
control sort of the most energy towards
your goal. So, if you need to do some
particular thing, you want to be able to
do it by inputting the least energy and
getting the most output back from that.
And this is what control information
sort of is talking about here. And this
is what I believe reorganization theory
has organisms looking for. It's looking
for these informationational bits that
will allow the organism to achieve its
goal most quickly.
And then there's also this notion of
whatformational bits change the goal
that the system pursues. I think this is
interesting too because it could be oh
you're seeking to go get food but it's
really really hot so you have to control
your temperature and thus do something
else that will help you move towards
your goal most efficiently.
Okay.
So now summarizing perceptual control
theory
for PCT behavior is the control of
perception. Organisms are natural
control systems.
PCT is grounded in the physical world
through insisting that variables be
measurable. Typically in PCT we're
creating um equations that are very
biohysical, physically grounded. We
don't have a bunch of different
variables that are not measurable. We
want to be able to even if we have to
crack open something and look inside, be
able to measure the thing that we think
is driving the behavior of the organism.
So we should be able to actually find
that internal reference variable when we
do some sort of dissection.
And PCT uses TCV to differentiate
between open loops and closed loops so
that you know what it is that you're
studying and how you should actually
approach it.
And finally, we have PCT. Perceptual
control theory aims to increase, I would
say, the knowledge of control
information. The way that things are
organized in such a way to be able to
achieve tasks with sort of minimal
amounts of bits.
Cool. So now we can break into going
into the free energy principle.
and the philosophy behind that.
Okay. So again another I would say
principle-based framework
and the principle here to put it like
very simply is if something exists it
must be doing something that allows it
to maintain its existence.
And level two, that thing that it does
can always be characterized as
minimizing variational free energy.
Okay. So there's obviously some sort of
physical thing that it is doing. But the
idea is that free energy principle often
is is very instrumentalist very a bit um
it can be at least researchers who use
FE can be a bit loose in the way that
they're saying that organisms embody
generative models. And so that makes it
sort of definitely different from
perceptual control theory in that
perceptual control theory is very much
about being in the actual physics. We
have to know precisely what are the
physical things we can point at and
measure that correspond to our equations
to our model of the thing. Free energy
principle they are allowed they allow
themselves typically researchers allow
themselves to be more loose with it. And
I bring up this paper here by Mel
Andrews where they talk about they
[clears throat] titled their paper the
math is not the territory.
And this is great because it just
essentially says that maybe we should
look at free energy principles seriously
more as a model structure rather than
specifically a model conr where we're
saying something about the world beyond
our senses. Maybe we leave it as just
the math and then leave it up to the
researcher to come through and point at
and say, "Oh, well actually I think that
these are the things that correspond to
these particular beliefs." Like this is
its prior here and this is how the
likelihood looks and this is the the the
mechanisms that are doing that. But it's
not something that I often see in the
literature whereas again PCT is centered
all around it.
Now getting into the sort of mechanics
of the free energy principle. How do
they justify saying that well if
something exists then how we can use
minimizing variational free energy to
model it in a sufficient way. Well, it's
the Markov blanket [snorts] construct
where when you're looking at something,
it must be maintaining some internal
states or some variables, right, that
allow you to identify it as the same
thing consistently over time. And so
what that allows you to do is break up
the system and its environment into
external states, internal states, active
states, and sensory states. where
external states are the states that
belong to the environment. The sensory
states are what are responsible for
taking the observations of the organism.
The active states allow the organism to
actually interact with the environment.
And the internal states is the brain.
It's sort of driving all of the things
there. All the physiological variables
that are happening there. And so what
this marov blanket construct does is
that it allows you to say the internal
states are independent from the external
states given the active and sensory
states but also vice versa that the
external states are independent from the
internal states given these blanket
states.
On the right here we can see the same
thing. It's a basian network or causal
graph if you will that just illustrates
how the markoff blanket actually looks
in the mathematical structure of that
the FEP often uses. And so we have here
the internal states which can be more
than one node or more than one variable
but here you can consider it just a
variable by itself. And so the internal
states has children. The marov blanket
of this will be its children, the
parents of its children, but also its
parents. And so that is how you see this
little circular marov blanket visually
going on right here.
>> [snorts]
>> And so what this does is it licenses us
to use B theorem where we can talk about
the hidden external state that we don't
know or that the organism I should say
doesn't know and we can cast its
behavior whether it's controlling or
doing something else as doing the
minimization of free energy to find out
what are the hidden states or the world
out there beyond my senses. that are
actually causing my senses. If I hear a
noise and when I'm in the forest, was it
a tiger or was it a tree branch that is
snapping? It allows you to cast
organisms as doing this inference in
order to survive. And so I have B
theorem here and it shows the posterior
and the posterior is [clears throat]
one's new beliefs after they have
observed some event like noise for
example. So how this works is that you
have a prior probability of what you
think the world is like beyond your
senses. So if we have this very simple
world here where we just hear a noise
and we think that what could have caused
it is a tiger or a tree branch snapping
then we have certain odds associated
with either of those. If we have a
balanced situation maybe we give 50%
weight to a tree branch snapping 50% to
a tiger being the cause of the noise.
But we could also given that we are I
don't know in in the forest and maybe
there's more tigers in this area than
particular we'll raise the probability
and say that there's a 75% chance of a
tiger and there is a 25% [snorts]
of the tree bench actually snapping.
Okay. And this is something that your
likelihood actually does for you in this
situation. You start out with these
prior probabilities and then we're using
a likelihood, the actual the probability
of the observation given this state to
help lead us towards
new prior beliefs that will be more in
line with what we with with our our
model of the world given the actual
[clears throat]
given the actual observations that we
see over time.
>> [snorts]
>> And so down here we have this marginal
likelihood and the marginal likelihood
is the likelihood and the prior across
all possible states so that we're
normalizing and getting a proper
probability for our new prior that we
experience.
Okay. So the problem here is that in B
theorem we can't use B theorem directly
because this marginal likelihood is
often intractable or impossible to
compute when we do this we can have
finite states and that typically helps
but if we have an infinite range of
possible states that we must consider
like in the case of temperature when
we're from 0° F to 90° F well we have a
value for 40.36289
9 Fahrenheit etc and so forth all the
real numbers from there which is
intractable and so because of that we
end up using variational basian
inference and indeed the thought is not
that things out there are doing perfect
inference and so variational basian
inference lends itself to being a better
more realistic way to actually model
things out there in the world you could
say [snorts] at least it is more
practical for us to use to be able to
understand things out there in the the
world. And so I've rearranged the bay
theorem taking the marginal likelihood
that's often intractable and making it
our target instead and moving the
conjectured prior the the posterior over
here. And the idea is that in
variational basian inference we
introduce an approximate posterior. And
if you were able to somehow guess what
is the correct approximate posterior
then you would also know what is the
marginal likelihood essentially. Yeah.
And so this is a way that helps me get
intuition for sort of what variational
basian inference is doing. However, then
you may ask oh well how do we pick the
the correct Qs? Like how how do we know
because it could be really any value.
and maybe multiple values give us give
us a place to get somewhere. So [gasps]
what free energy principle does is it
helps you find a QFS an approximate
posterior distribution that minimizes
your free energy or your uncertainty
with respect to the particular model the
that you're using to do your
observations and that is this joint
distribution that's constituted by the
numerator here in Baze theorem
and to just like give some sort of
fundament ments. I want to go through
the mathematics just of the variational
basian inference from the from the
beginning but very quickly just a quick
sort of run through to hopefully be able
to translate this again more intuitively
all in one spot. Okay. So what we're
looking at here is just the conception
of Shannon surprise or entropy local
entropy of a variable. So if we had this
variable here, probability of X, we
could say it's probability of heads or
tails. And so that's going to be 50%.
And if it's 50%, then we're over here.
And our amount of surprises, it's quite
low, right? And it just gets lower and
lower and lower, the higher the
probability of the state is. So if we
actually had a coin that was totally
rigged such that it gave us heads all
the time and we flipped it and saw
heads, we wouldn't be surprised at all.
And if we were to flip a different coin,
right, and it had a very very low
probability of heads, then we would be
very very surprised to see heads. And
this is what sand and surprise does for
us is it allows us to quantify our
uncertainty about some probabilistic
variable
given given uh what we see. Yeah.
And that is just matheropy
equal to the logarithm of the reciprocal
probability which gives you that really
nice curve that we saw before. But then
there is also the wider or global
entropy that we more normally use where
instead of just considering the state of
of heads, we consider both the state of
heads and tails. So it's just a summary
of telling you well how surprised would
I be to see heads and how surprised
would I be to see tails? How surprised
would I be to observe generally the
state of this random variable?
Yeah, it is also looked at as the number
of bits necessary to encode the
particular distribution that the
probability represents. So it's another
very cool and interesting
interpretation.
And then getting into finally the
variational basian inference maths.
Well, it uses the coolback leler
divergence to tell the difference
between the two distributions
[clears throat] between two
distributions. And so the idea here is
that
we're going to have [clears throat]
our distribution that we actually know.
This is just what comes up in the
literature. So, it's really helpful to
have this KL divergence here raw where
we're just using single distributions
rather than joint distributions. As you
saw hopefully in the quick flash in the
next slide here, we actually have the
joint distributions that we use in
variational free energy. And so this is
just a slide to
help people along and see where it comes
from where we're using just basic
variables. And now when we're looking at
this and also seeing how we actually
derive this sort of klar divergence
mathematically and so when we're looking
at this we're introducing right here our
approximate distribution. This is our
approximate posterior. And then right
here we actually have our posterior that
we really really want. And we want to
know what is the difference between our
approximate posterior and our possible
our new posterior our new beliefs. And
the idea is that since again it's
intractable to actually do regular
basian inference then what we do is we
find the minimization of free energy of
uncertainty with respect to this
particular model and that entails us
actually blowing this up into a term
here that we call free energy where we
have the marginal surprise on the
outside because it's sort of the
intractable part and then since because
the coolback leler diverg
can only be uh greater than or equal to
zero. Then you're able to use this to
minimize free energy and thus find some
sort of
some sort of distribution that minimizes
your free energy with respect to your
model to make you more accurate given
your model. And I think that's very
important that it's not like the global
solution. It's not truly the most
correct that you could be about your
observation about the causes of your
observation but it is the most correct
you could be about the causes of your
observation given your model given that
you have limited constraints to do full
basian inference. So you do this
variational sort of inference here to
make this happen. And I put this here
because this is the variational basian
inference without your
policy without your actions. This is
just simply observing and it's simpler
to mathematically derive. But then we
also have on the bottom here including
your policies, including your actions.
And this is essentially demonstrating
how you do both parts. the variational
free energy but then also the expected
free energy where variational free
energy says okay what do I believe is
the most likely state of the hidden of
the world given my observation and
expected free energy says well what do I
expect to see given that I do this
particular thing
and given my model
and this allows the organism to reach
its
preferred observations. It's
observations that it would like to see
in the world that would help it survive
and move through and do all of the
things that it does.
Okay.
So
here I'm just showing that we have the
free energy here on the left and we can
break it down or look at it another way
as the expectation of the difference of
logs and that we can further say okay
well we're taking the expectation with
respect to the approximate posterior
distribution. Well, if we take that
away, then we have this sort of general
setup where we can go, okay, this is how
you get free energy. Well, we'll take
the expectation with respect to
the approximate posterior distribution
of the hidden state given the policy.
And that gives you this sort of thing
where you can take the [clears throat]
generative model component and break it
down into these two probabilities which
give you this interesting interpretation
of the model where it's complexity minus
accuracy. So how accurate I am versus
how much I am actually changing my
beliefs. And you're sort of having a
balancing act there which is why they
call this an optimal way to update one's
beliefs. The variational basian
inference sort of gives you a way to
look at that mathematically and and make
this interpretation I feel like in a way
that you couldn't do with just uh bas's
normal formula at least the intuition
doesn't seem for me to be there. We can
also take this and do an expectation
with respect to the generative model
like this. And we end up getting this
equation here which with some
approximations the approximate posterior
from the variational free energy
calculation and as well as taking
[clears throat]
instead of well our just our policy and
the consequences that it has on our
observations. Well, we'll think about
well what are the the pref preferences
that I have and the consequences that
this has on our observations. What is
the pragmatic value that I'm getting
there? And so this is the information
gain. How much am I learning from this
observation if I change my beliefs like
this versus how much does it actually
matter for me in particular? So there's
this do I go and get the information
just because I will know more or will I
go and get it because it will help me
survive. And that's the sort of
pragmatic value option that's happening
here. And this just brings it all
together into a complete slide so that
um hopefully it can be a helpful
resource for someone out there. Okay.
Summarizing
free energy principle. So for free
energy principle, the behavior of
organisms is driven by what any organism
expects will allow it to achieve its
preferred observations or its goals. And
that this is sufficiently described by
Baze rule or variational inference
expected free energy minimization.
And I think the FEP is best looked at as
a model structure with no onlogical
commitments and that the commitments
should come from the modeler. At least
you can you can look at it this way. In
other words, you could do something like
test for controlled variable where
you're actually measuring things and
identifying whether this is a control
system and then you're building a
generative model about perhaps the
beliefs that this organism has about the
reference variables it's controlling.
You I don't think that you need to use
straight up differential equations after
that. And so again, you can use the math
and not have ontological commitments
saying that this thing out there that
I'm modeling really has beliefs, etc.
and so forth and is really doing
inference in some sense.
Cool. So jumping into the modeling
section, we have modeling bacterial
chemo taxis.
The idea with modeling bacterial
chemotaxis
is that it's ubiquitous in biology. You
see it everywhere. Not bacterial
chemotaxis in particular, but chemotaxis
in general where in the brain we have it
controlling where our neurons actually
end up during development in the immune
system navigating towards viruses and
things like that. Even with inside a
cell, you have mitochondria that are
following ATP gradients. And so
chemotaxis is everywhere in biology, but
it is extraordinarily simple. It's like
well understood but really really really
important.
It works by just comparing the
difference in concentration of some
particular molecule at two different
positions in space. So for the case of
the E.coli for example, you can imagine
that we have a sensor right here and a
sensor right here. And due to that it
can know whether it's going in the
direction that is increasing the
concentration gradient that it's seeking
or decreasing the concentration gradient
that it's seeking.
So interestingly bacteria cannot
actually choose a particular direction
that they're swimming.
They must randomly tumble. What they do
is they they trigger all of their
fugella. It causes them to do this sort
of spinny thing. They pick a new
direction and they go that direction
until error increases and they do sort
of you could call it reorganization
again to find a better policy or path or
thing to be doing such that it allows it
to minimize its free energy or
eventually reach its goal of no
difference between the reference
variable and the sensed variable.
[clears throat]
And so, not only can it not control
where it's swimming, but it also
experiences this thing called rotational
diffusion where due to the medium of the
liquid that it's in, its viscosity,
it'll be swimming in some direction and
it'll get disturbed randomly and that'll
shove it off course. And so, it'll have
to sort of deal with that too. And it
does. We see E.coli, they they do their
thing. And they call this a biased
random walk. That it looks really random
the path and trajectory that it's
taking, but it gets to its target and it
gets to it much more quickly than if it
were actually going in some random
direction all over the place simply due
to rotational diffusion. Um, and so what
we did was make models of this in both
perceptual control theory framework and
free energy principle framework.
Yeah.
And this is a diagram that illustrates
perceptual control theories model. Dr.
Richard Markin and Dr. Bill Powers, they
wrote a paper on modeling bacterial
chemotaxes with PCT and we reproduced
that reproduce that in lockep using um
TypeScript making some programs in the
browser. [snorts] And this is what it
looks like. So you have XY and these are
just your positions of the E.coli. We
have the E.coli in red right here. And
we have its actual swimming angle where
it's going in this direction. And we can
also calculate the angle that is going
towards this uh target which is you can
think of it as a sugar gradient. then it
doesn't quite actually
it doesn't [clears throat] start
collecting food until it gets into this
area which just gave gives us a metric
to kind of think about um how much how
close it is how much time it spends
towards the center. So this gradient
here reflects the actual concentration
of food but outside of it there is no
such concentration. We're only using
this angle system to get it towards
there. So in some sense this is not like
a biohysically accurate realistic
uh model [clears throat] of bacterial
chemotaxis. It's phenomenological and
we're using this functionality here as
sort of a surrogate for how bacteria
actually sense using sensors at the
front and back of themselves and
navigate towards this thing. Another
point here to make just early is that we
don't actually have rotational diffusion
going on. So there's no real
disturbances that are going on when we
have bacti
bacteria navigating towards its target.
Now we have this position here. We have
the angle that it's actually swimming as
a we have the angle towards the target.
And the perception is this difference
between the cosine between the actual
angle and the angle that it's swimming
times its velocity times this g constant
factor which in the literature was just
one. So you can pretty much ignore it
for the purposes of this here. And then
we have our error which is simply the
comparator. We're min we're subtracting
the perceived signal from our reference
signal. We're using that error to
accumulate a kind of accumulated
historical error. And so we add this up
down here where we're adding DQ to Q.
And if Q is larger than Q, some some
capital Q, some threshold, then the
bacteria tumbles. And the idea is that
the bacteria needs to tumble in such a
pattern or such a frequency that it is
able to navigate towards the center of
the chemical concentration gradient.
And next thing is modeling bacterial
chemotaxis with FEP. I'm going to show
the results of how each of them look
later after we go through these details.
And so here we have the likelihood of
the generative model that this bacteria
embodies and we have the prior pro
probability of it being in a certain
place. And so for the states we just
have near to target, mid to target, far
from target. At first our prior state
probability is that well we don't know
where we are. So we're going to spread
our beliefs or confidence over all of
the states. And here we have the
likelihood which actually tells us how
likely is the observation uh given this
prior knowledge. [snorts] And
[clears throat] so you'll see that I
have the near at the top here but then
also this angle here. And so what this
means is that okay well if I'm facing
between 0 and 120 angles to the target
then how how close do I believe I am to
the target? Do I believe that I'm far
near or mid from it? Similarly here when
I'm looking in this direction, my
swimming angle is in this direction or
in this direction. Well, like how how
exactly, you know, confident am I am I
in my belief that [snorts]
[cough and clears throat]
that this angle actually represents how
close I am to my target. And then we
have this equation down here. Low = 1 -
high / 2. It allows you to make a sort
of proper probability matrix
where you can have say high is 90. So
we're going to have 0.9 and this will be
90 and then this will be five and this
will be five. Similarly this will be
five and this will be five. So it turns
it into a proper probability
distribution where you're peaked at a
particular point meaning that you have
high confidence. I think that the places
that high goes because we could sort of
rearrange these constitute different
hypotheses
about sort of where how likely I believe
I am to be close to the target given the
angle of my swimming direction in
relation to the target.
And here this is a precise example of
it. This is a precise example of it
right here where we have the actual
values filled in.
Cool. We also have what's called a
transition matrix. And so the transition
matrix is what's used in our expected
free energy calculations where we're
wondering about given that I'm taking
this action versus that action. Well,
what do I expect this state to actually
be be so that I can come up with what do
I expect my observation to be given that
particular state? And so the this is a
transition matrix for approach where I
have 1 minus NB NB NB over 2 0%. The
idea is that this is a non-locality bias
and sort of just like where the the
placements of high inside of the
likelihood matrix give you a sort of
different hypothesis about your beliefs
of the angles relationship your swimming
angles relationship to how close you are
to the target. Well, this gives you a
sort of idea of what's your belief in
the world being non-local. So it if you
have a high non-locality bias, right?
And in this case, I've actually set
these straight up to zero% so that the
so that [clears throat] there is no
chance that you have too extreme of a
non-locality b uh bias. So, if you
believe you're near on the first time
step, then you're not likely to believe
that you're you're you're 0% likely to
believe that you're far on the next time
step after taking an approach action.
And so, this is the transition matrix
for approaching. And it doesn't mean
necessarily approaching the target, but
it means for going to continue in the
same direction that you are going.
Okay.
Then we have the transition matrix for
the tumble action where after tumbling
we have 33% across all of them. So
essentially you are
not
anymore you have no sort of bias towards
where you believe you will be in
relationship to the target after
tumbling. It's anybody's guess.
And then I have these log preferences
here. And so this is the template log
preferences
where
these preferences are not probability
distributions. They are log prior
preferences. And so only the
differences or the the relative
magnitudes of the values inside of this
vector are what count or what matter.
And the more positive, the more
favorable, the more negative, the more
unfavorable. So in this situation, since
we have 0.00 corresponding to 020,
then we have a preference for going in
this direction and we don't prefer to go
these other directions. Again, not going
away from but towards the actual target.
And so there are a lot of different
trajectories that came out between these
two models.
This is wobbly and then stuck where we
have perceptual control theory ecoli on
the left side and the palm dp or free
energy principle e.i on the right side
there. And this is wobbly then stuck.
But we also have wobbly then loosely
stuck. [sighs]
And we also have
very straight then stuck
and trajectories like very straight then
loosely stuck.
I took all of these and collected them
by hand after simulating a bunch of them
and trying to look at, okay,
how much do the behaviors of these two
models actually overlap? So that way we
can get to a really solid comparison of
maybe which one might be better than the
other
and be able to then choose what
explanation we'd like to do going
forward. And I think that there are many
trajectories that are unique to PCT or
unique to POM DP, but I wasn't able to
actually [clears throat]
quantify that in a way that is more
quantitative rather than qualitative
rather than just kind of handpicking out
different things. And I attempted to use
a machine learning algorithm. I think
that that would be really really
helpful.
But this was outside of the scope of
what could be done inside the paper with
the time that we had deadlines.
So these are the results quantified for
PCT where you can see the distribution
of the average distance from the target.
We're only looking at um the PCT ecoli
that were actually able to reach the
target. And similarly here we can see
the distribution of food collection time
ratio which is essentially how long did
it spend inside that blue target but
also how long did it kind of spend
towards the center of it. How how stuck
was it after it actually got there and
we have the same thing going on for the
FE results quantified.
And the thing is about these is that I
feel that the conclusions are hard to
draw. It's hard to draw any broad
conclusions from this due to the fact
that I could not do a sort of
quantitative
estimate of it. And the thing is that I
was able to pick parameters that would
make PCT win or FE win this competition
very very easily. It seems that any
results that I had were super highly
dependent on the parameter space. And
for that reason, I feel not comfortable
with being able to justify one or or the
other given this situation.
Okay.
I think I want to say here that there
are there's definitely future
opportunities to do better comparison.
We could look at sorts of different
metrics and perhaps actually get some
sort of quantitative way to for instance
analyze the trajectories of both PCT and
FE. And instead of doing it
qualitatively like I did where I just
picked through ones that had similar
trajectories, you get this principled
way of actually binning all of the
trajectories by trajectories into
different categories that are
independent from the model that actually
produced it. That way you could say,
"Oh, these are the parameters that
produces these types of trajectories in
the PCT
uh model and these are the parameters of
the FE model that produce trajectories
that are in that same category." And
then when you do that, I think you'd be
able to make a more solid fair
comparison
because at least you'd know that they
are having the same sorts of
movements.
Okay, so getting into the mathematics of
it of the mathematical comparison of the
two PCT versus FEP, I chose to use
category theory. Category theory is
called like a mathematics of
mathematics. It's super simple and
general and for that reason it's just
highly expressive. I' like to call it
sort of
Yeah. Yeah. So right here, this is what
makes up a category. Any category in
category theory and this is just a toy
example of a category. There are serious
categories like the category of set or
the category of groups.
And here we have objects as different
types. And so types are
it could be I like to think of it as
programming language types where you can
have booleans, integers, etc. so forth.
But it can be sort of any thing that
you're considering to be an object that
you have it being well defined. Um so
for example we could have people here
and people have cats. Yeah. And we have
integers and we have booleans. And so
this morphism that is is a function that
essentially tells us what people how
many cats do they have when I'm given a
particular person. And then you have
another morphism here. G is integer
greater than two. Well then how many
cats do they have? Maybe it's three. Is
three greater than two? All right it is.
And then so you get a boolean output as
a result. And the composition of G
follows F. these morphisms would be do
they own more than two cats and I'd like
to call composition like a program um
and associivity
is like syntax so when you have G
follows F say you could have G follows F
follows H and you could have parentheses
around G follows F but also parentheses
around F follows H. Well, then depending
on where you put those parenthesis is
actually changed the object whether or
not the object is the same. And so this
is what associivity or syntax is doing.
You need to have these sorts of
coherence rules to make your you have a
a proper category. Objects morphisms,
composition, and associivity allows you
to do that. And this is sort of you
could call it the the category of cat
owners or something like this. I like
that category theory is so expressive
that it's quite easy to make sort of
um diagrams that are rigorous and formal
yet not entirely completely
mathematically rigorous and it gives you
a way to sort of zoom in to specifically
what do you mean by people the people
object in this thing and make it more
complex more rigorous and so in that way
the category theory that I'm about to
show you here is not the very
mathematically rigorous category theory,
but more like how people have pseudo
code where they write up pseudo code
before they write up some very specific
program. Well, you can have sort of
pseudo category theory where you use
this to develop real more intense
rigorous category theory. And so that's
what we're going to get into next after
talking about these couple structures
that are
helpful tools from category theory where
once you have an actual category let's
call it category ABC well we can have
category XYZ2
and then we can have a funtor between
them where we're mapping the objects and
morphisms from one category into the
objects and morphisms of another
category. Furthermore, we can have
morphisms between functors and these are
called natural transformations which
help you understand the ways in which
different categories.
So if functors tell you the relationship
between different categories and you can
have multiple relationships between
different categories, natural
transformations tell you how those
relationships themselves are related.
Okay.
So I created this PCT agent category
here where I have the input quantity
with has that is taken by the input
function into the perceptual signal
which is then taken into this sort of
tupole here where we have our reference
and our perceptual signal from which we
calculate the error then pick an action
and finally the output function leads us
to our output quantity which affects
what I put here calling it the
generative process. Not a term term that
perceptual control theory typically
uses. We call call it the environment.
But in general, I've made all of these
arrows black to indicate that they are
part of the environment and not part of
the organism that we are considering. So
that you can see this sort of
environment or organism coupling
just here inside of the diagram.
Okay. And then we also have our
disturbance. So the idea being that the
environment sort of produces the
disturbance that then affects our input
quantity that our perceptual control
theory organism is controlling.
So now this is the
H. Okay. So [clears throat] now this is
the free energy principle agent category
where I am showing variational basian
inference in this categorical form. And
so we have the generative process here
which outputs the observation and that's
why I put the GP in the perceptual
control theory diagram to just kind of
get at a little bit of similarity to
hint more at between hey you guys are
calling this this and they're calling
this that. just so we're all aware
generates this observation. We observe
this perception. Yeah. And we create
this observation and prior state tupil
here, if you will, where we remember our
prior belief about what the possible
hidden state of the world is. Then we
want to imagine new beliefs about what
could have possibly caused this thing,
this observation that we see in a way
that allows us to be more consistent
with our model. And so we take this SN
which is Q which is our approximate
posterior distribution or yeah and we
put that there.
Finally, we get into
our
variational free energy where we're
coming up with the hidden state that we
believe caused or our possible hidden
state that we believed caused our
observation. And with that you can
calculate the expected observation. What
do you expect to observe given that
hidden state? And then you can consider
the expected observation by putting it
into this tupil here where you're going
to consider it during your next action.
And so down here on this other path
which is like the goal path something
like this where you're trigger
triggering your memory of a preference
and we're bringing in the preference
here. You're remembering your prior
preference. We're combining it into this
tupil here and we get our preferred
observation. What is it that we'd
actually prefer to see? Not just what is
it that we expect to see and then we
remember this preference and together
with the pref the preference that we
remember and the what we expect to
actually see we calculate our expected
free energy which tells us given this
situation
what can I do what do I expect will move
me towards my preferred observations in
the future what actions should I
possibly take and so this gives you a
sort of expected free energy a list of
your actions paired with quant
quantities that tell you which one of
them is most likely to minimize your
which one minimizes your expected free
energy given your model of the world and
then you take that action. It influences
the generative process and you continue
the loop all over again.
I also have this category here and this
is the category I put of of Hodgekin
Huxley neurons. And so this is just to
show that when you're doing perceptual
control theory, we are talking about
biohysical equations too. It's not just
the diagram there. Whereas when we're
talking about the free energy principle,
the diagram that you saw previously is
is that's that's pretty much it. We're
not super often concerned with a mapping
between that free energy principle
diagram and some particular biohysical
equations and I think it would actually
be really really hard to do that but is
definitely an interesting endeavor and I
know that there are there is work in
actually understanding how for example
neurons uh encode different likelihoods
and priors etc and so forth and so this
diagram shows the category of Hodgekin
Huxley neurons
where we're looking at the neuron as a
circuit and it's controlling its voltage
is the best way to look at this. Neurons
have a resting potential and when
they're deviated away from that
particular voltage, they always end up
coming back to it due to the ionic flows
that are happening inside of the neuron
and across its membrane.
So we can look at this now where we see
the Hodgegkin Huxley neuron diagram next
to the PCT agent category diagram
and show how we have a functor that maps
from the elements inside the Hodgekin
Huxley neuron diagram to the objects
that are inside the perceptual control
theory diagram. And this gives you a way
to understand Hodgekin Huxley neurons in
terms of perceptual control theory where
you say okay I know what is the input
quantity what is the output quantity
things that I could potentially measure
and I understand that what is causing
what what is the reference signal that's
causing it to actually end up back at
that resting potential that I see it
characteristically returning to every
time it is disturbed by some particular
current from whether that's the outside
or internally generated current. And
this is really what you're dealing with
when you're talking about modeling with
perceptual control theory is that you
have to have this whole side of
biohysical equations or equations that
you're using to model the particular
parts of the thing that you then uh
shove or relate to this diagram.
Okay.
So now we get into the actual comparison
between free energy principle and
perceptual control theory here where I
illustrate that with this funtor here,
it's kind of like a a forgetful funer,
maybe you could call it, where we forget
uncertainty.
And the idea is that we're just losing
all of the parts where we're explicitly
handling uncertainty because that
information in perceptual control theory
would just be handled by sort of like
entirely different models. would be oh
which one do I pick and I don't actually
write that down and represent it in in
my model itself
and you can take this functor and break
it into subfunctors which when glued
together will give you back this
original thing but it helps you clarify
different aspects of how these two
categories are related. So you can see
the internal variables in the free
energy principle category being mapped
to the internal variables in the
perceptual control theory category. You
can see similar things happening over
here for perception and action as well
as uncertainty and certainty where this
shows you precisely how we're forgetting
the uncertainty handling in a sense and
this shows you just sort of [snorts] I
would say maybe they're they're more
similar than different at least when it
comes to perception and action [snorts]
something like that in any case these
reveal different sort of
facets to the comparison that has been
made by this FEP to PCT functor.
Cool.
So a potential synthesis then I see lies
in the dual interpretation of the free
energy principle where instead of
looking at organisms as if they have
beliefs about the outside world, well
you can flip it and talk about the
beliefs that you have about the
organisms that are then going and doing
things. And so I think that this would
be sort of like modeling our beliefs,
our own beliefs about control
information about how these things
should be particularly organized. So
instead of beliefs reflecting things
that I might not be able to measure, I
make beliefs about the equations that I
know have variables that I can measure.
And you could sort of think about this
as having beliefs from functers from the
biohysical equations to PCT diagrams.
Well, I have the Hodgekin Hugsley
diagram and I have funers from it to
PCT. But then I could have another
different sort of neuron model with
functors again to PCT etc etc and so
forth. So I have that a whole set of
them. And then I make some sort of
belief probability distribution over my
understanding my mapping of
>> [snorts]
>> my description of the outside world and
sort of my conceptualization of the
outside world too.
So it's beliefs about the organization
of biohysical equations I think also is
another thing. So thinking about perhaps
[sighs]
if we have this whole entire pool of
biohysical equations and we want to
understand something out there that is
producing data, can I somehow make some
sort of interesting belief structure in
terms of the free energy principle that
allows me to take all these biohysical
equations and organize them in such a
way that I have a model now that is
reproducing the data that I actually
measured and organized.
uh that I actually measured from the
world out there. [snorts]
And if we could do this, I think it
would be really really cool to be able
to generate a bunch of different
things that are physically grounded with
the biohysical equations using our sort
of knowledge that we've codified but
codified inside a particular model
structure something formal something
rigorous. So rather than like you could
say how maybe PCT and in general folks
do it now where we have biohysical
equations different ones for every
particular thing. [clears throat]
We can have a situation where and and we
don't know which one maps to which thing
out there. We can have a situation where
we're encoding our beliefs about how we
think that these should be organized and
be mapped and then we're generating
models and things simulated things based
off of that and then we're seeing the
data that they produce and then
comparing that to the data that we
actually collect in reality. I think
that would be interesting because if you
could do this then you would have a sort
of maybe if not scale free at least a
way that your models are immediately
physically grounded to the thing that
you're modeling rather than just taking
some arbitrary model and fitting it to
what you see outside because it's not
really necessarily going to give you
measurable variables. You could do this
and you would definitely have measurable
variables. You could go out and actually
test your theory as you are generating
your theories.
And so future work elaborating both PCT
and FEP models of chemotactic
chemotaxis. It would be really really
cool to see how hierarchical structures
and conflict inside of perceptual
control theory map onto the more
complicated models of free energy
principle using greater depth but also
uh hierarchies. So both wide and tall
and deep and seeing how these two things
can synthesize
in an applicable way. So developments of
hybrid PCT FEP models but also seeing
how both of them compare to each other
using category theory. And hopefully
category theory can give a good way for
lighting the way for how we can actually
synthesize the the differential
equations the biohysical equations that
we use in perceptual control theory and
physics traditional physics with the
sort of I don't know newformational
physics type free energy principle stuff
that we do with the probabilistic
generative models. How can we know
exactly how it is that these physical
organisms that we see entail or embody
generative models? And how can we ensure
that for example
this physical medium could never have
this generative model because of X, Y,
and Z, but this one has it could only
possibly be this generative model
because of A, B, and C. I think that
would be really really interesting and
important. So
that's it. Thank you. Awesome.
Thank you, Ty.
>> Thanks, [snorts] Ty. It's amazing.
>> I just want to say one more thing. Being
with the Florida Atlantic University, of
course, I'm with the Center of Future
Mind and in Dr. Rodrigo Penna's lab
where we study computational
neuroscience, corransmission, biohysical
modeling, and things like this. You can
check out my website typhoons forthought
where I have like lists of projects that
I've sort of done over the years and
games which is a way that I started
thinking about all this uh quite some
years ago. It's just a simple toy model
where you can think of
the biohysical equations and stuff
that's going on as being pieces in a
game and the free energy principle
that's organizing all of these pieces is
being player in a game. And so it's kind
of a [snorts] interesting new very early
development of a theory towards making
this all cohesive in a simplified
manner. Okay. Thank you.
>> Awesome.
Okay, Warren, first if you want to
provide any remarks.
>> Oh, thank you. Thanks, Daniel. Uh,
thanks for hosting this. Um, and I just
want to say, Ty, thank you for such a
comprehensive talk and it just validates
our collaboration over this last year
putting this together. You're you're the
only person on the planet that can
actually articulate these two theories
clearly with respect to one another and
then communicate it to a wider audience.
So, I'm kind of I feel honored for that
reason because there's been so much
tension and conflict and
misunderstanding on both sides, thinking
they're the same, thinking they're
completely different, etc. And this
piece of work actually starts to um
identify where those overlaps and those
differences are. Um, I think I I mean
everything that you've said is um uh
everything you've covered is is a is a
is a a real foundation to what's going
to come next. Um I just want to clarify
a couple of things. Um one is that as we
know the model that you've shown of the
PCT
unit is just the model of the um
fundamental unit of PCT a control one
control unit. The theory itself proposes
that these units are organized in a
branching hierarchy of multiple levels
and that there are at least 11 of these
levels that Bill Powers has identified
as identifying um um abstracted levels
of um perception of the outside world.
Um so you know people can look at that
in more detail but I think what it
illustrates is that we've compared a
subset of PCT the kind of the basic
subsystem of PCT with the whole of FE
but actually when you when you think and
you start and you would start to model
these units in these uh complex
hierarchies and then you have to
understand that reorganization you saw
He had the great diagram there from Bill
P showing that the reorganization system
actually adjusts the parameters of those
systems. And Bill Pals proposed that
what we describe as conscious awareness
is the spotlight that finds those units
that it's going to adjust the parameters
of in order to update and um improve its
control. Um so it opens up to
understandings of consciousness but it
also I think provides a lens to think
about how those parameters which you had
to kind of just cover the whole possible
range but actually within PCT you've got
this reorganizing unit that um finds and
adjusts the parameters that are going to
work for the organism itself and we
haven't really got to that point where
we can understand that and also I think
that that once you build that part of
the model in, you can see what looks
like uncertainty. You can see the model
evolving and adapting. And when we see
that from the outside, we can see this
organism still fumbling around trying
trying to learn. It's having uncert
uncertain states because its parameter
space is is not fully crystallized. And
then as that parameter space narrows we
it looks like an organism that's getting
more certain but like you say what it's
actually doing is kind of tightening
these bio biohysical parameters to um to
a structure that you know fulfills it
its goals and and maintains its
survival. Um so I think that's one thing
I wanted to say. The other thing I
wanted to say is watching your talk now,
even though obviously we've worked on
the paper together, I was actually
thinking of the parallels between you
using category theory and what I've kind
of had to put into the PCT model, which
is a category interface, which was
actually suggested by a colleague Martin
Taylor. um a category interface between
the perceptual hierarchy and a
propositional system, a system that
actually codifies the variables in the
in the PCT hierarchy as uh as symbols
and then tries to understand the
connections and the coariances between
all those elements. And I I feel that a
theory like FEP is much better attuned
for understanding those propositional
beliefs of a working system um than like
you're saying the biohysics itself. And
so I am starting to see a kind of a
fusion, but the fusions for me it's the
the PCT stuff's over here in the in the
in the lived hierarchy in the embodied
hierarchy and the the FEP is sitting
beside it through a category interface
and making these hypotheses about the
state of the world in in a more um in a
kind of more of a reality testing,
belief testing way rather than a a way
that's purely about uh functional
adaptation. Uh so yeah, they're my few
words. I hope it makes sense um in light
of what you've been doing.
>> Absolutely. I would love to know more
about that about like precisely how
you're, you know, codifying and building
up that system. Definitely. And seeing
how
>> I'm not doing it with coding or maths,
just dust pictures and words. [laughter]
>> But that's always where it starts.
>> Yeah.
Very cool.
>> Awesome.
Okay, Andreas, would you like to give
any reflections and questions?
>> Yes. So I just want to u congratulate
you Tai and Warren and uh your PI on a
really ambitious project you know like
so you're really thinking about the big
picture and I think that you're really
providing a service uh to the world by
relating two different um
uh world views and and just seeing you
know do they connect can they say the
same thing in two different ways and
maybe that says something about um just
like how different levels of awareness
can interact and so on. Um in I wanted
to ask about the category theory. Um
are you mentioned the forgetful funer
and I was curious are you familiar with
adjunctions?
>> Nope not yet.
>> So uh I've studied category theory uh um
you know on my own quite a bit. Uh I
have a PhD in math and I would say you
see there's kind of like a cult of
category theory. So it's it's a little
bit um I don't know it's a little bit of
funny feeling towards it. A lot of it is
verbiage. So it's just words and words
and words and words that really aren't
very helpful. Uh but there's a couple of
very deep ideas. So one is the yona lema
which is the fundamental theorem. The
other is adjunctions. And so what
adjunctions are doing in which you're
kind of speaking towards is how do you
it's the mathematics of analogy. So how
do you have a window in one world and a
window in another world and they match
up on that window? Okay. And so there'll
be a funtor taking you from the one. So
instead of category I just say world you
know but you think you have like a world
of free energy principle you have a
world of um um uh perceptual control
theory. And so the funer that goes from
the free energy principle to the uh C
PCT world is forgetting. It's forgetting
like you said uncertainty. So now
imagine if that same information exists
in both worlds, how do you go back? And
that function is called free
construction. Okay. So there's got to be
a way and it's it very much relates like
to the maximum entropy principle. was
saying, look, if you don't know nothing,
but you're just going to freely
construct things, right? What would
uncertainty look like? You see, what
form would it take? What shape would it
take? And then you would automatically
get some kind of system that would make
sense in the free energy principle
world. Do you see? So, that's a super
deep idea. That's a super big win. And
because of the just bold way you're
thinking, you get to go there, you see.
But when I hear like you talk about
pseudo category theory etc. It's kind of
like pseudo Chinese, you know, or pseudo
arithmetic. It's likeing, you know, you
know, it does not, it's like a horse in
a tuxedo, you know, it really does not
contribute because when you a diagram is
not a category for many reasons, but the
problem is is that the objects you
mention, you're not clear on what an
object is, right? And the morphisms,
they need to be composing. It's not
clear what a morphism is. You know,
there's huge problems in it just seems
so much more straightforward if you say,
"Look, we're not going to mess with
category theory. We're just going to
work with diagrams, but we're going to
use ideas from category theory because
you don't need to see your strong part
was the philosophy." Like your
philosophical analysis was very,
especially in the paper, just very
astute, you know, and just very
informative.
This dressing is is just so bad. I can't
imagine that why how they could review
it and accept it. It's just really bad.
So, you know, you don't need to be
hurting yourself that way. One and so
maybe I'll just maybe that's my first
comment. I don't know what what but
that's from my heart.
>> Uh that's fair if you don't think that
it it's because I called it category
theory. Basically, it sounds like it's
if I just called it diagrams, it'd be
fine.
>> If you said I got diagrams and this is
how I think about my diagrams, you would
save a lot of energy and you would save
a lot of trouble. you wouldn't be
stepping you know in puddles. I don't
know you know why stepping in puddles
you know you you just have your own
theory of diagrams and your theory of
diagrams may end up being much more
informative than category theory because
category theory has got problems
basically in terms of how it's
developed. So the other thing maybe to
to say it's fantastic like I think the
chemoteaxis is an interesting thing but
to focus I think on how to make it as
simple as possible. So the things that
you did were absolutely unconvincing and
just seemed like not to the point. But I
think the idea to say, hey, here's these
two different things. How would they
model chemotaxis? So for example, one
problem is that you're having it go to a
point. But what if you just had a it's
really about a gradient. What if you
just had a gradient from left to right
of the screen and let's say you have
something in the middle and you send it
up. Now, what's the chance it's going to
end up going in the right direction in
the gradient? Right? You see that should
be a much more illustrative problem
because it's just really one like can it
read a gradient and then to look at that
very philosophically like in fe it's
about memory if you're going to it's
really a question like when they're
going through that gradient are they
remembering and measuring that it's
weaker now it's stronger or weaker later
right or like with CPT is it saying I
have a set point I have a preferred
density right and I don't care what the
gradient is I'm just looking for my
preferred density
That's kind of hard to believe. It seems
like they're both trying to want to
have, you know, but in order to get the
gradient, they have to have a memory,
but they would implement the memory
differently. And so what's the minimal,
you know, problem to say how are they
implementing memory and then compare
that to the actual known biology, you
know, how see, so that would take it
make it real. Whereas what you're doing
is very it's like fanfiction, you see.
So, you know, is Star I'm going to
compare Star Trek and Star World and
how, you know, Star Wars and how do they
compare? Well, a lot of FE, you know,
are you doing fanfiction or are you
doing science? It seemed more like
fanfiction.
>> I see what you're saying. That's
interesting because I feel like I I
addressed both points. I think they're
super real. I think that you have to
start somewhere. I like you draw
pictures and you do words before you get
into rigorous mathematical equations and
stuff. That's why I said that with
pseudo code, pseudo category theory. I
know that Toby Maguire Smith is uh
working on category theory of FE and
like being really rigorous with it. Very
long epic dissertation that I have not
gotten to dive into yet. And then
similarly with the bacterial chemotaxis,
it's like well I could start with
biohysical equations and really go there
that way and get really specific. also
with the FE side, but just starting
somewhere and then using that for future
work.
>> I'm not saying to use biohysical
equations. I'm saying just simple things
like
just the like a little diagram of a
bacteria. What do we know, right? Like
we know that if the if the things if the
fleella turn one way, they separate and
you get tumbling. If they turn the other
way, then they unite and you get, you
know, direction in one way. Okay, so
there's an onoff switch there, right?
What are the receptors like? You see,
you don't need to have any biohysics
thing, but you need to be able to say
how does memory work, right? Like what's
the what's the what's how does memory
function? So, um maybe just to conclude
that um I think you're doing all these
great things, but like maybe the
fundamental thing is that with your
philosophical analysis, you gave a
rather critical view of both and
basically like they both could be wrong
or basically not very wellounded. you
were both missing the big picture, but
then you kind of like it's as if you're
reconciling them, you see, but maybe
they don't deserve to be reconciled.
You're not really treating them as real
scientific theories that could be false,
you see. So, I think that's the problem
is I I believe they're probably both
problematic. Yes, Warren.
>> Yeah. I guess just a couple of things
there. I think one one is that you're
you're right. You're absolutely right
that the the main the goal of this
project was not to falsify one or other
theory and I think that is a a a
direction that needs to go where they
can be a proper adversarial
collaboration where where both halves
both theorists propose a model in
advance of testing the model and that
the results of that model or the design
is set up so that it can actually
differentiate between the two in
advance. I think that would be a a gold
standard. Um the other thing that is a
direction from this and and Ty and I
have talked about this. We were in a
kind of a debate about whether to use
the Markin and Powers equations or
whether to come up with their own. We
use the Markin and Power equations
because they were published and
associated with PCT. Um but actually
when you look at how they've um as Ty
explained inferred the perception of the
gradient there's no way that the um
bacterium itself through its biohysics
could calculate that angle cuz we've got
the privilege of a of a high level
perspective on on the bacterium. It
doesn't. Um what my hypothesis is that
is that the controlled variable is um
the the rate of gradient change. Um
because if you're going directly towards
the um the the source of food then um
you the change in in gradient should be
zero. Whereas if you're slightly off
track then as you move then that
gradient should gradually should uh
gradually dip until when you're
perpendicular to the food for food unit
then it reverses.
So but we haven't been able to in the
time frame kind of implement that
controlled variable. I think that would
be a step towards being a tighter
version. But I think if you if we could
then combine that with a um kind of more
of a pre-registered planned hypothesis
test then we would get closer to this um
uh way of testing the two the two models
more directly. The other thing that
we've not mentioned is is just the
basics of parimony. You know if two if
two theories can achieve the same ends
which is your preferred theory for me
personally my preferred theory is the
more parimonious one. And we do allude
to that in the article as well
>> and that you really do a good job of the
tension between the two theories. And so
for me like I think that that's a
fundamental thing missing by itself on
the FEP and maybe on the other theory
too that if you have like two levels of
awareness like unconsciously a mind that
knows the answers unconsciously but
consciously a mind that does not know is
divorced from reality. So it's always
interrogating asking questions right so
you can see those two theories like one
is very physically real and the other
one's kind of like very conceptual and
that's a very natural interaction um I
would think then the problem is is that
like which is more relevant in which
situation so yeah everything could be
modeled predictively but is that really
does that mean that that's how things
are right and I would want to say
probably not so if you were a little bit
more adversarial like but sympathetic
but adversarial
you can maybe sort out like is there a
combination like you say they're
orthogonal you know so how does that fit
and how do they serve each other but
they need to be trimmed down both of
these theories are probably a little bit
more robust than they should be uh and
they should accommodate the other ones
better that's my thought thank you
>> okay
>> yes lot lot here as we sort of come to
to an end I think you raised a lot of
great points and I was also very struck
by how you took the math is not the
territory seriously. And even with
Warren's later illusion to that
categoric interface, there's this double
necessity of cognitive modeling to on
one hand be the spectator at the
baseball stadium watching the outfielder
catch the ball, the view from the
outside, and then the different
analytical ways that that problem could
be computed like as a trajectory with an
absolute destination and meeting it. But
it's also analytical to reduce the angle
of deviation from expectation. So the
spectator is always in that analytical
mode. And then the spectators are
debating my model is more biohysically
grounded because I'm actually modeling
this. And so they're having that
conversation. But then as you pointed
out like I wondered about the 1/3
breakup or the angle of deviation and
then as you brought up at the end of
course the bacteria doesn't have access
to that angle.
So then that's like the low road to
active inference is building joint
distributions that cover the whole
iguana, the kind of whole cognitive
model being its own proof existence that
the bacteria does do
chemotaxis.
And then that that
openness of modeling from the outside
where we have all these different
theoretical traditions, different
ontologies, sometimes just the same
variable with the same name. sometimes
same variable, different name. All these
pieces that with your wireboarding,
>> you're creating the conditions for there
to be a falsifiable discussion around
rather than just sort of two ships
crossing in the night and giving a
starting point for software and
approaches to start testing them in
terms of utility. But just fitting
better or having fewer variables or
doing better on a benchmark
could never falsify a model in
principle. So theory will always be the
refuge for those who have a certain
abstract perspective. And then on
specific settings there can be the
direct comparison of performance of
these different models which kind of
brings us to the computer science and uh
AI adjacency of these fields in this
very fascinating way even though they're
so deeply grounded in longer
philosophical traditions and even
embodiment. And so I think you brought
together a ton in the paper and uh in
sort of closing question mode. Uh not to
be too committee oriented, but just what
are you hoping [snorts] to see in the
coming years of grad school? Like what
steps do you want to take moving this
forward?
Um [clears throat]
it would be an elaboration of everything
that I've done here. So especially the
things that Andreas talked about like
going for how exactly let's get more
specific than just the angle towards the
thing. let's actually look at the
biohysics so that even if we don't go
fully biohysical, we can talk
specifically referring to how this is
actually going on in bacteria and then
connecting that to generative modeling
and like I said previously also going
more really indepth into the mathematics
in the category theory and like really
really really fully unpacking the
relationship between these two sorts of
things and how we can get them to maybe
make a hybrid model that's not something
cobbled together because right now I
sort of imagine it as just like FEP
stuff, PC stuff, and really just
cobbling it together. And I think that's
a it's a starting point, but it's all
really just a starting point.
Um,
yeah,
>> I I wanted to and I like Daniel's
comments and I wanted to uh just add
about the baseball thing that uh that
tension between the subjective view were
like you're seeing the ball coming at
you and the objective view were like you
could actually measure the angle if you
knew the whole, you know, if you were
able to to to see it from that angle.
See, that's like a common filter. So
we're like you're one person is taking
measurements let's say you know by
watching the ball but another person has
a theory they have a theory of of how
balls move you see and so you can
connect in control theory you can
connect those two types of things it's
very meaningful to have both vantage
points
>> h I could see the spectator with their
camera or perception having a common
filter and then also the outfielder with
their common filter and then that
categorical interface and then a sort of
total cognitive accounting starts to
connect the onlogical realism and the
biohysical mechanics of what's happening
for that bacteria where there's so many
papers on the enzyme phosphorilation and
the actual decay rates but the project
and the scope wasn't necessarily to make
this atom uh level biohysical simulation
and that is the question is once you
start coar graining
and not just doing the atomistic
simulation, you are in the space of the
map and the territory.
So, and and that's where there's all of
these amazing questions and and
directions for students. So, thank you
Ty, thank you Warren, thank you Andreas.
>> Good good luck with the work and till
next time.
Thanks for
>> being part of this. Brilliant. Cheers.
Cheers.
Okay, V strong. So, I'm thank you. Thank
you for this and uh I hope to be in
touch then somehow one way or the other.
Goodbye.
>> Super. and Ty, we can uh touch uh touch
base again